you
now picture then that we shall be using
why is it 3 because that comes after
example to Jesus false we shall take
this rather unusual approach that even
in dimension about one when we cannot
strictly speaking draw a graph in the
elementary sense like this when we have
to draw something like this we shall be
graphing that have to use
metaphorically graph vector fields
metaphorically like this um this is
vertical and then we do it's just like
this okay
that's the graph of this vector field
here is literally true here it's already
metaphorical well mathematics is a
metaphor in this metaphorical picture
abstract picture
where are the equilibrium as a
pronounced it's here here right worthy
vector field vanishes where the vector
becomes zero so your initial question
was absolutely spot-on it's correct we
are interested in equilibria we are
interested in where this graph this
metal graph intersects the y-axis so to
speak but please realize that although
I'm drawing the picture like this one
dimension one dimension in fact M can be
a high dimensional space and this has
correspondingly higher dimensions in the
last example M is two dimensions and B
is also two dimensions okay right that
was the preparation systematized is a
little bit by definition is not much of
a definition is more of a notation
suppose M is a manifold
and little X is a point on the manifold
lots of examples here when I say X I
don't just mean x-coordinate I mean name
of a point it can be any dimension we
shall introduce a symbol the collection
of all the tangent vectors tangent to em
at upon 2 X such a collection forms what
is called the tangent space
Oh M and X and it will be denoted by how
do you know the tangent space it's going
to be denoted always by T sub X of M T
as in tangent so you really tangent to M
X this is a natural generalization of
tangent line here the all the vectors
are along the x axis here all the
vectors along the X Y axis as long as we
are
excuse me okay
well I meant well there's no shame okay
well away so we taught you my tangent
space but in those examples you don't
see what we mean because the vector
fields were drawn on flux spaces real
axis and just a real plane but suppose
that we have a vector field which is
domme on some curved surface like this
then do you have a choice we have to
draw a vector at each point on the
surface and all I'm saying is that at
each point I should draw a vector which
is tangent to the surface like this
something like this vector pointing
straight out of the servicer so that's
not what we are considered to be sure in
vector calculus analysis of dr. fields
and so on sometimes we consider normal
vector fields and so on but that's not
what we are going to talk about we are
going to talk about only vector fields a
tangent to the surface game okay hence
the tangent space and we are saying that
if you take a point for example X at
this point we can think of all the
vectors tangent to this surface and that
collection is tangent
okay I hope you can visualize this
sometimes tricky now an even trickier
concept is the tangent bundle he might
be the first time you need this world
bundle but at least I'll spell it more
visibly vu n VL e bundle the country
bundle of M is simply for us the
collection of all kinds of planets
tangent spaces the on T M is the
collection of all tangent spaces
I thought once
so T of em you can think of it as the
Union as excellence all the T M of T to
M X in fact there is a more complicated
definition about tangent bundle is but
we will not really need the official
definition you can intuitively think
about oh this tangent bundle is I'm
thinking about all the tangent spaces at
all the points at the same time okay
that's enough
as an intuition okay that was more of
that but the important thing is at each
point to think about all the tangent
vectors at that point together and you
think of the tangent space at that point
and then over the entire manifold you
can think of all the tangent spaces at
the same time and that collection is the
tangent bundle okay let's draw another
picture this is another abstract and the
metaphorical picture a tangent bundle to
the manifold he of M may be visualized
as follows
maybe visualize locally but not
necessary glory
I'll come back to this local versus
global contrast in unity one later on as
just a product of M times a vector space
of dimension and so what I mean is the
following thing let's say that Emma
looks like this and at each point you
might have some value of the vector
field the vector field can take many
different values depending on what the
future's so I'm going to draw very
strangely the tangent space to M at this
point as a vertical axis you might say
that's absurd because I'm supposed to
have vectors that tangent to M pointing
in the direction away but we cannot
really draw this if we are going to do
this picture the second picture so
imitating that second hand picture we
shall do this at this point for example
at some another point X prime this is
the tangent space to M at X prime and so
on so we collect all those and tangent
spaces together okay and the collection
of all of these I'm kind of drawing this
kind of picture is the tangent bundle
okay so the vertical axis here is the
vector space of dimension equal to that
dot V and I'm this entire picture is the
picture of tangent bubble okay it's
the most confusing concept in this
course but I hope that you can code okay
so it was each tangent space is in this
picture drawn vertically so of course in
reality
Tisa f X of M is by definition tangent
to so it should be along the direction
of M but it's the same idea that we have
for the this grass visualization now and
let's then do on the graph of a vector
field just as we have been training in a
rosemary succeeded and succeeded
so we shall generalize what we have done
let's recall that by a vector field on
and on we always at least in this course
mean
hunting camp for example if you have a
circle like this you might want to cause
the vector field which looks like this
you know it points out but then he
points this way he points this way he
went this way
and in pointing this way and it kind of
comes back with pointing this way at
each point of the circle you have a
vector so it is a vector field you might
say on the circle but we don't say the
vector field on the circle because
whenever we mean when we say a vector
field on a sample we really mean about a
few that's tangent along the side okay
so this is not in our terminology and in
the family most mathematicians nowadays
not electrocute on this one so please be
careful we are always saying tangent
vector fields now a vector you
v/m can be visualized every
locally ass as a graph gonna be like
this we draw a favorite picture and
together with lots and lots of tangent
spaces and you consider all those spaces
together and this is the vertical axis
all of them
you see I'm drawing the space em i
between the current way because it's
often curved it's not a flat space off
and the entire thing is tangent bundle
and you consider the graph a function
which looks like this
that's gamma of P and for the one last
time as as I pointed out in the
beginning will be interested in
equilibrium of this vector field and in
this picture the two degree are simply
equal to those points
let's grab console graph gamma zero what
does that mean
it simply means the graph of the vector
field whose vector value is zero
everywhere that's what it means right
because graph of B is the graph of the
vector field whose value is V so this is
because of the vector field value zero
everywhere and this thing of the
everywhere zero vector field that seems
to be a very uninteresting vector field
so in the original picture example you
come up here
I consider another vector field where at
every point x and y the vector that I
associate is zero zero so here I can
move here I don't move here I don't move
no way I do that move that kind of zero
vector field is nonetheless important
for a reason TOC is called the zero
section the graph of the a zero vector
field is called zero section and we
vector field representing the zero
section is the area zero vector field
that sounds like complicated but it's
very simple so we have the following
assertion that gamma 0 is simply from a
morphic to the following thing what is
the graph of 0 if you are going to draw
it here naturally you can see 0
everywhere so this is in fact from a
more active a means of so M can be
thought of the under my mind fault can
be thought of as the graph of some
deficit
this is good news the equilibrium of V
those points where the Grafton yogev the
field intersects the zero section and
got it more intuitively if you like are
the points X where G of X becomes zero
but this is if you like more elementary
and analytics point of view this
regarding equilibria as the intersection
of two graphs is a more modern and
modern point view that leads to post
architectures okay
I met inside here panel which lead to
your entertainment to solve the puzzle
is as follows
let's Polly give number
please try to they're generally
generally in general under civilian RT a
vector field on s1 has always an even
number of equally
and even number OS that's Julius in the
example that we started from that
example an odd number so on the line are
one you can have an odd number of
equilibria but I'm saying that if you
draw the picture of any vector field on
s1 please remember that when we said all
as one that means tangent along s1 that
vector field generally must have an even
number of equilibria why is this please
figure it out it sounds like a slightly
mysterious statement but if you take the
point of view of the graph of a vector
field of the tangent bundle in fact the
puzzle becomes completely obvious so I
hope that you enjoy doing this okay
now I continue to introduce the
description of a theory and this
definition is very familiar in fact we
should compare this with the concept
that we introduced the definition for of
the previous chapter there we were
talking about the fixed-point theory and
we were talking about the sign of fixed
points whether each fixed point is plus
or minus how can we talk about the sign
well we represented math as a graph of M
cross M and then we will consider the
diagonal and we saw that the fixed
points are exactly where the graphs
cross the diagonals diagonal and those
points where it crossed were exactly
fixed points and we can say whether the
intersection was positive or negative by
the orientation we used orientation
theory we reduce the theory of fixed
points to that of the theory of
intersection under here it's more the
same idea but instead of the fixed
points we are talking about the
equilibrium and we reduced the name of
the index index or V an equilibrium
x is plus 1 or minus 1
o minus 1 accordingly as the sign of the
intersection of the intersection
between the zero section and the gravity
vector field and you have to make sure
that you account in the mean we saw that
because you can't it ended all that the
orientation might slip soda at X is plus
one or minus one
I hope this is clear
although the sentence is very long in a
special case if you think of em as
one-dimensional then this
this is also one dimensional and with
the standard notation the zero section
is really end so what's this side of the
intersection at this point it's gamma
zero this way and gonna be this way
so that's that's positive and that's
negative that's positive so those are
what we call the index indices or vector
view that those ones it's always plus or
minus one and you imagine that we are
going to add up those illnesses and that
one becomes the intersection number
between those two manifold sub manholes
that are zero section and graph for the
left field indeed your guess is right
Travis nothing between decks of X where
I sum over all the equilibria X if you
add them all up this simply becomes the
intersection of zero section
because we know the intersection theory
and we got useful its use in the context
of fixed point theory and this comes as
no surprise we need a screen here to fix
this
okay
well as usual all this discussion
concerns when the intersections are
generic or transversal
when there are some degeneracy such as
you know and the with the field comes
down but just glazes the zero section
and goes up when the tangent each other
so then we cannot really talk about plus
or minus one it's a regional situation
but as usual if you have a degeneracy
what we do we will deform and part of
the picture a little bit and then the
general she disappears resolves itself
to a generic situation correct
so as usual if those two objects that
less than zero section on the graph and
not transversal in the
America so apparently imperatives
respect ice hammer classes they are not
if they are not we should try to
popularize this pronunciation around the
world you know study from eggs you can
now not in still think transversely
interceptive as a humble heart I mean
let's show that much nice okay if
they're not into transversal
trustus intersection and then country
index and I think the case of the
intersection theory it doesn't matter
how you cut up the index that you obtain
in whatever way you perturb the but the
fugitive transversally will always be
the same
is that and I should be transported okay
now you remember when we discussed the
index Olivia six-point theory after
discussing all the abstract concepts we
wrote down a formula do you remember the
formula said that the plus or minus one
depended on the determinant of the
derivative of the map minus the identity
matrix and you come to the science and
added and so forth there was a somewhat
complicated formula and you remember
that we didn't really use that formula
in major applications such as the
browser 6.0 it was enough to understand
the picture of what we're doing know
that such formulas can be useful if you
are facing a concrete problem given in
terms of firmness firmness so I'm going
to write down the corresponding for job
in the case of the better field theory
so how do you calculate this index of V
of X in actual practice companion is
with the discussion of the previous
chapter and I think the formula was also
called formula 8 formula 8 not funda 1
it's 8 times better than formula 1
suppose that then D is expressed
explicitly as a former locally in
components as V 1 at X 1 to accept and
vm x 1 i hope this calculations familiar
to you from vector calculus red lip
curled and so on Stokes formula
divergence theorem Gauss's theorem and
so you have vector field so yeah M
components will deduct the field at each
point if you add the point X 1 an
experiment song then you calculate what
this value is you calculate the next
values and so on
and the components of the vector
whatever you numbers come out okay so
Saturday are your own when we were not
yet awake but a little confused because
we are saying at the point 1 0 0 1 you
have to calculate those components and
kind of the minus 1 0 something like
that vector is
at that point and so okay so that's the
the representation suppose that you are
given the vector field in this form
which is quite often the case then it
turns out that this index of V at X can
be written simply as follows you first
calculate the derivatives of this map
mean if there is only one component and
one variable I just take the derivative
in the standard calculus sense of high
school but if you have many components
and many variables what we do we have a
Yacoubian matrix exactly so this is a
poly matrix and I take the time and then
I simply take the sign on this and
that's the index for V X please note
that in contrast to the fixed point C V
we don't have - data in the fixed point
case with AB - I'll adapt it that's
because of the following you see in the
fixed point case we are comparing the
graph together with a graph compared
with our diagonal has not one or in
multiple variable case the derivative of
the data is the identity matrix so
because we're comparing the graph with
the diagonal we have to look at the
difference between the derivative
Yacoubian and the identity matrix here
however we are comparing the graph of
the but the field will be zero section
and the zero section actually has
directly which is zero so this is the
difference between the Jacobian and zero
that's what you don't have - that's the
difference between defects
theory and this vector field discussion
okay
is miss really believable I hope it is
let's go the picture when the dimension
is one here's a picture let's consider
so this is really a one dimensional
picture for once the picture we're
drawing is completely realistic let's
say that we have the vector field whose
graph is represented by something like
this okay that's the vector field and
the zero section is homeomorphic and can
be identified with mindful itself and
the usual orientation applies in the
ambient space so in this same logo
direct product of M and r1 the
orientation is 1/2 like this locally
it's a direct product in that case what
are these signs or the indices of those
equilibria for example here it's plus
and it's easy to see by now for you
most of you have notice that if it's
going up it's plus netiquette dance -
it's basically the right intuition
you'll see in Division 2 and above that
that intuition has to be modified
because we don't have anymore going up
and down but all the signs let's see
what the index is according to the
formula just if I'm not yet proving me
this formula but I'm checking with an
example view that
from the make sense so index is plus or
minus one that correspond to as we saw
the derivative of the X and the X in V
and X is positive or negative right if
it's positive that means going up plus
one it is negative it's going down
- index is - okay but let's see what
this really means so when you have the
negative intersection like this that
means on the personal M that this is an
equilibrium and you have a vector field
which on this side is positive in other
words on the side is coming in to us
right on this side is negative so it's
coming in towards death you see what the
character of this equilibrium is it's an
attractor everybody around it is coming
in to us and such a thing is called a
sink everyone sings so this is a minus
one and in the part of the picture like
this for example here here and so on if
you look at the corresponding picture on
the actual manifold itself well on the
right-hand side of this equilibrium
it's possibility that means that the
open is running off left right and on
this side to the left and see what the
character of this equilibrium is
everyone is going out from you and such
a point you know such a point suppose
it's called a source exactly
so source and sink can be distinguished
simply by looking at the derivative if
there is positive or negative source and
sink in one dimensional case and those
correspond
index plus minus plus minus